<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second Christian warning-piece wherein is shewed the first and chief cause of England's present misery, proved to be the chief magistrate's neglect, in not fully doing that work God hath commanded, that must yet be done, because God hath said it, before this nation can expect deliverance. Humbly presented to the Parliament.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829951</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34398</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1941:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second Christian warning-piece wherein is shewed the first and chief cause of England's present misery, proved to be the chief magistrate's neglect, in not fully doing that work God hath commanded, that must yet be done, because God hath said it, before this nation can expect deliverance. Humbly presented to the Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Tho. Wall.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Duties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34398:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Second</hi> CHRISTIAN WARNING-PIECE; <hi>wherein is ſhewed the firſt and chief Cauſe of</hi> England's <hi>preſent Miſery, proved to be the Chief Magiſtrate's Neglect, in not fully doing that Work God hath commanded, that muſt be yet done, becauſe God hath ſaid it, before this Nation can expect Deliverance. Humbly preſented to the PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe moſt wiſe God, who uſeth the Miniſtry of his glorious Angels in the Government of the World, hath alſo ordained ſome Men to be Governours in the Nations: in which weighty Work that wiſe King <hi>Solomon</hi> had ſome of the prudenteſt Men in his Kingdom, to give counſel in times of greateſt danger, for the Preſervation and Peace of his People.</p>
            <p>2. Your Honours, by the Providence of a gracious God, are the King's Majeſty's moſt grave Counſellors in Parliament, gathered together at ſuch a time when this, if not three Proteſtant Nations, are in moſt apparent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Deſolation, not only by the many Judgments of Plagues and Fires already come, but many more threatned; by reaſon whereof the Nation, as it is a Body Politique, its <hi>whole Head is ſick, and Heart faint,</hi> ſo that from head to foot there is nothing but Wounds, and Bruiſes, and putrified Sores, full of Corruption; which in the eye of Reaſon cannot be cured only by cutting off ſome dead fleſhly Traitors, and ſo think thereby to heal the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on's Wound; when as the chief Cauſe hath not yet been look'd into, not known, and ſo cannot be removed, therefore it ſtill breaketh out afreſh, more dangerous than at former times; as hath been proved by many years wofull experience. Therefore it is the opinion of the ableſt Phyſicians, when a Body is deſperately diſeaſed, the Cauſe muſt be enquired into; and, when known, the Means ordained of God uſed for removing it, before there can be a Cure either in the Body of a Man, or a Nation.</p>
            <p>3. The truth of this your Honours may ſee in Holy Writ, that the Lord, in the days of <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſent a ſore Judgment on that Land of three years Famine; and ſo long it continued until the Cauſe was inquired into by the King and his Council, and when it was known to be for the ſin of King <hi>Saul</hi>'s bloody houſe, for deſtroying the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> his Subjects, whom by Oath, according to the Covenant made with them by <hi>Joſhua</hi> and all <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> before the Lord, he ought to have defended and preſerved: But ſo ſoon as King <hi>David</hi> gave order that Judgment ſhould be executed, God was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34398:2"/> immediately entreated for the Land. O that this may be well minded by your Honours.</p>
            <p>4. Becauſe the Lord ſendeth not his ſore Judgments, either of Famine, Sword or Peſtilence on a Nation, eſpecially on his own People, without a juſt Cauſe, as is proved by another Preſident: When God commanded King <hi>Saul</hi> utterly to deſtroy <hi>Amaleck,</hi> becauſe he murdered the Lord's People, when weary and faint in the Wilderneſs, as they journied to the promiſed Land: and for the negl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct hereof God ſuffered an <hi>Amalekite</hi> to kill King <hi>Saul:</hi> and alſo, by reaſon the Lord's Work was done ſo negligently, the whole People of the <hi>Jews</hi> in King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his Country were near to be deſtroyed in a day by the Plottings and Contrivances of that wicked <hi>Haman,</hi> the ſeed of <hi>Agag</hi> the King of <hi>Amaleck,</hi> had not the Lord marvelouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it. And whether theſe things, in a figure, are not the cauſe of the preſent Miſery and Danger this Nation is in, let your Honours be Judges.</p>
            <p>5. Becauſe the Lord having commanded the Kings of the Earth, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Kings, to hate the <hi>Whore,</hi> to wit, of <hi>Rome,</hi> utterly to make her deſolate, according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. becauſe ſhe, as a ſecond and ſpiritual <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck,</hi> murdered the Lord's People, making her ſelf drunk with the Blood of Saints, as they are travelling in the Wilderneſs of this World towards their everlaſting Reſt; ſo that becauſe a part of this Work was done by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of happy memory, (when they aboliſhed out of this Nation the Lord Abbots, Cardinals, Jeſuits, with ſome other of her Abominations) and is not fully finiſhed, but neglected by the King and his Parliament, God had almoſt ſuffered the Kings Majeſty (whom God preſerve) to be murdered by four <hi>Ruffians,</hi> the ſeed of the ſpiritual <hi>Whore;</hi> becauſe all the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Inventions, either in Miniſtry, or other of her yet remaining Abominations impoſed by Law of overſight on the Conſciences of the King's Subjects in <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, and for this ſame Neglect, whether the whole Nation is not in as much danger to be deſtroyed (as the <hi>Jews</hi> were in <hi>Mordiea</hi>'s days) by the Plottings and Contrivances of the wicked <hi>Hamans</hi> of that Popiſh blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty Generation, your Honours can beſt judge.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Becauſe the King's Majeſty, together with your Honours, will not bear with ſuch an affront from any foreign Princes or States, to impoſe upon you ſome of their Laws and Officers to be joyned with yours in any of the Offices, Cuſtoms or Orders in Government of the Nation: No more will the Lord Jeſus have impoſed on him in the ſpiritual affairs of his Church, any of the Offices or Traditions of the Popes, Prelats, or any other not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the Word of God, without incurring his high diſpleaſure. And for Confirmation hereof, I ſhall make bold to lay before your Honours theſe four Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34398:2"/> 1. As light and darkneſs can have no communion together, no more (ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.) can <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial;</hi> that is, Chriſt in his Ordinances, and the Pope or his Prelats in their Traditions and Inventions, joyn'd in Worſhip together; but as the Lord deſtroyed them that ſet the Ark of God and <hi>Dagon</hi> together, and conſumed his own People in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>that</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43. 8.) <hi>ſet my Threſhold and theirs,</hi> Me and Them, mine Ordinances and their Abominations <hi>together in Worſhip:</hi> How can <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for theſe things think to fare any better than thoſe Idolaters afore-mentioned, let the wiſe in heart judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If God made the <hi>Canaanites</hi> as thorns in the eyes and ſides of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they defiled themſelves with their Abominations, and made a breach in the Covenant made between the Lord and them, who commanded them not to meddle with their Inventions in Worſhip, nor make Marriages with them: May it not be even ſo with theſe Nations, becauſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have defiled themſelves with many Popiſh Inventions in Worſhip, and alſo becauſe many do make Marriages with the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> hath not God, ſince the Reformation began, even for theſe things, made the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as thorns in the eyes and ſides of this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Nation, I leave to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to judge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Lord did vex the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with all Adverſity, ſo that there was no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in, becauſe they worſhipped God with another Miniſtry, and Inventions of King <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s making: and becauſe they kept the Statutes of <hi>Omri,</hi> and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> walking in their Counſels in Worſhip, contrary to the Law of God given by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for which the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make them deſolate: how ſhall ſuch <hi>Proteſtants</hi> believe any other, that worſhip God by a Miniſtry of Man's making, with many Popiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions alſo, but for it God will ſtill vex this Land with all Adverſity, as by woful experience is ſeen this day; and, if we be not warned, in the end the Lord may juſtly make this Land deſolate: as when no means would cauſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> to return to the Lord's true Worſhip, the Land did ſpue them out.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe the Lord's People of old, by Covenant made between him and them, were his eſpouſed Wife, and he their Husband: and the fellowſhip and communion they ſpiritually had together, was as in a Bed of Love, ſo long as ſhe, as an obedient Wife, yielded obedience in all things that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to his Worſhip, and to no others Commands and Directions, either in Miniſtry, Ordinances, Time or Order: but when <hi>Judah</hi> did defile her ſelf with the <hi>Babyloniſh Inventions</hi> in Worſhip, the Babylonians were ſaid to come in to her <hi>into the Bed of Love, Ezek.</hi> 23. 17. for which God threatned them, as a Woman that brake Wedlock, to give them into the hands of the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34398:3"/> her Lovers: Even ſo under the Goſpel, the Lord's People by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Goſpel are eſpouſed or married to one Husband <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who is the Head of the Body his Church; and ſo long as ſhe obeys the Commands of her Lord, the only Arch-Biſhop and Paſtor of his Flock, ſhe is ſaid, in the performance of his holy Ordinances, to have fellowſhip together with him as <hi>in a Bed of Love.</hi> But when thoſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that ſo account of themſelves that they are the Lord's People by Covenant, and Chriſt their Head and Husband, do yeeld obedience to the Commands of Popes, Prelats, or any other mortal men, in the Worſhip of God, ſhe (as an Harlot) is ſaid, with Antichriſt, <hi>to take their fill of Love together, as in a Bed;</hi> Prov. 7. 18. Now if no honeſt Man will endure that his Wife ſhould yield obedience in Marriage-duties to another Man, becauſe Jealouſie is as the Rage of a Man, that he will not ſpare in the day of his Anger, how then ſhall the Lord? becauſe <hi>Marriage is honourable, and the Bed undefiled, but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge;</hi> ſo that the Lord will not ſpare in the day of his Anger. O that theſe things might be well minded by all good Proteſtants!</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Right Honourable and Noble Patriots,</hi> ſeeing for the Evils aforeſaid, firſt, for the King's Majeſty, together with the Parliament's neglect to obey the Commands of God, in making the <hi>Whore</hi> (to wit, of <hi>Rome) deſolate,</hi> in aboliſhing all and every thing that hath but the ſmell, ſcent, or taſte of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, either in Place of Truſt in the Nation, or in Place and Office, with their Traditions in Worſhip, ſet up by former Kings by Law of overſight in <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, for which the Lord is angry not only with the King, and your Honours, but alſo with the whole Nation. And for the doing of this glorious Work, that there be no erring on the right hand nor on the left, I humbly beg leave to lay before your Honours theſe three Obſervations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The wiſe God hath given the King's Majeſty, together with his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Council, moſt perfect Directions in this his Work of Reformation about the Worſhip of God, by example of the Godly Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> who had no power by their Civil or Kingly Authority <hi>to add to, or diminiſh from the Worſhip of God, but to remember the Law of Moſes,</hi> as a moſt perfect Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for all things in Worſhip; ſo that when any King, by the counſel of falſe Prophets and Teachers together, or in his own heart, did deviſe or ſet up in Worſhip to God, or to the worſhip of Idols, any thing either by way of a falſe Miniſtry, or Altars, or Sacrifice, or any other thing aforeſaid, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God's Law, the Godly Kings of <hi>Judah, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> by the Command of God did demoliſh it, and deſtroy it out of their Dominions, and did call the Lord's People by all loving means to the Service and Worſhip of God, according as it was found written in the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And thus they were (as God had promiſed Kings ſhould be) <hi>Nurſing Fathers:</hi> not ſuch Nurſes, to give the Lord's Children Milk, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34398:3"/> doctrine of his Word (as is the Miniſters work) the Breaſts of his Church for Conſolation; but, as Nurſes, that look after with care, to defend and preſerve the Church from all enemies at home or abroad, that (Dragon-like) are ready to devour her Children, which the Church in her painful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry and Preaching, <hi>travelleth in pain till Chriſt be formed in them,</hi> begotten by the ſeed of the immortal Word; that ſo as the Pſalmiſt, Prophet, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay, <hi>this and that Man was born in her;</hi> Pſal. 87. Iſa. 66. Rev. 12. Gal. 4. And this is ſtill the duty of Chriſtian Kings under the Goſpel; not to add or diminiſh, but to preſerve the Church while ſhe followeth her Head and Husband <hi>CHRIST</hi> in all his Directions in Worſhip, and to demoliſh all Images, and falſe Inventions and Traditions ſet up by other Kings in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to God; that ſo the <hi>Romiſh Whore</hi> may be made deſolate, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Lord turned away from this Nation, as it was when the good Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> did the ſame work, from that Nation. For what a ſhame is it to ſee in the Cathedrals in <hi>England</hi> how the Clergy bow and cringe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a wooden Altar, Papiſt-like!</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no King, nor other mortal Man, hath power over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of any of his Subjects in ſpiritual things: as ſaith the Apoſtle,<hi>—we have no dominion over your Faith.</hi> Therefore when <hi>Joſhua</hi> conquered part of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the Nations became tributary to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as their Subjects and Servants, they forced them not to be of their Religion; becauſe they, and all Kings ſhould know that it is a work belonging to God only, <hi>to perſwade Japhet</hi> (or the Gentiles) <hi>to dwell in the Tents of Shem:</hi> ſo that to force any man after that perſecuting manner (as do the Pope and his Prelats) to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, before they have faith, or be born again, is to force blind men to the Kingdom they ſee not, and to make a Church of Hypocrites, bringing men into a ſnare even to their Condemnation, <hi>to devour that which is holy,</hi> and after that (ſaith <hi>Solomon)</hi> they muſt with ſorrow enough make enquiry what they have done. Therefore the work of Kings is only to take off all the yoke of Popiſh Bondage, ſo that their Subjects may be free, ſeeing (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>every Nation will walk in the name of his God;</hi> that ſo <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as true Chriſtians, may walk in the Name of the Lord their God, whoſe Name is his Law, the Goſpel; that ſo as Chriſtians, they may do their duty to God, and love their Brethren, <hi>doing to all as they would be done unto;</hi> and in this is the whole duty of Man comprehended.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing <hi>God hath ſhewed unto man what is good,</hi> Mic. 6. 8. and then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially unto Kings, the Lord's Lieutenants, who, with their great Council in Parliament, are, (1.) <hi>to do juſtly</hi> (2.) <hi>love mercy,</hi> (3.) and <hi>to walk humbly with God.</hi> This will be, 1. when the <hi>Romiſh Whore</hi> is by Act of Parliament aboliſhed out of this Land; not in deſtroying the lives of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> that tranſgreſs not the Laws, but live peaceably as loyal Subjects to the Government in all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34398:4"/> Civil things, as well as other Perſwaſions, but to deſtroy all Popiſh Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations out of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches. 2. In <hi>loving Mercy,</hi> when the King's Majeſty with his Parliament ſhall make an Act, That no <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or any other living peaceably, of what Nation ſoever they are, ſhall not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for Conſcience ſake in things ſpiritual; eſpecially in the matter of Tithes, conſidering how many are daily caſt into Priſon becauſe they cannot in conſcience pay them, for theſe Reaſons: (1.) Becauſe Tithe was an heave Offering under the Law, aboliſhed by Chriſt, who was the end of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law for Righteouſneſs to all that believe. <hi>The Prieſthood being changed, ſo of neceſſity the Law,</hi> Heb. 7. (2dly.) Tithes were never payable but in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo never commanded of the Gentile Churches. (3.) Tithes were not paid by any Chriſtians for eight hundred years after Chriſt, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Writers ſay, and then Pope <hi>Paſcalis</hi> appointed Tithes ſhould be paid to his Prieſts. Therefore in paying Tithes, Chriſt is denied to be faithfull in his Houſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, to appoint a Miniſtry, and not their Wages; and the Pope made equal with Chriſt, in giving Laws to his Church. O that your Honours would find out a way to remedy this great evil, and take off this yoke from the necks of all Proteſtant Subjects; ſeeing <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>To puniſh the Juſt is not good, &amp;c.</hi> Prov. 17. 26. Then the 3d thing God requires is, That both King, Parliament, and all the King's Chriſtian Subjects <hi>walk humbly with God;</hi> and this will be when they ſhall worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, according to his directions in his laſt Will and Teſtament: That ſo Chriſt Jeſus may in all things ſpiritual reign in his Church: which was and is the true foundation of all promiſed Peace to the Lord's People. As for example, under the Law: So long as <hi>Iſrael</hi> worſhipped the Lord as he commanded them by his Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> in Miniſtry, Ordinances, Time and Order, God promiſed that they ſhould dwell in the Land in confident ſafety, <hi>Lev.</hi> 25. And when all <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Males went three times a Year to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to worſhip, and left none to guard their Dwellings but very aged Men and young Children, the Lord was a Wall of Fire about them, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2. in making their enemies to be at peace with them. And ſo long as the primitive Chriſtians feared the Lord, and worſhipped him, as Chriſt Jeſus had appointed in his Teſtament, the Churches had reſt throughout all <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, Galile,</hi> and <hi>Samaria.</hi> And thus, <hi>when the Lord giveth quietneſs, who can make trouble? but when be hideth his face</hi> (for the reaſons aforeſaid) <hi>who can behold him? whether it be done againſt a Nation, or a Man only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have diſcharged my humble duty, firſt, unto his Majeſty, and next unto your Honours, and, laſtly, to all the Nation (though the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitteſt of many) in a work of this nature; beſeeching your Honours not to deſpiſe it coming from ſo unworthy an Inſtrument, but remember that there were many wiſe Men in the City <hi>Abel,</hi> (for renown termed, <hi>a Mother</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34398:4"/> 
               <hi>in Iſrael)</hi> who deſpiſed not a Womans Counſel, when it was for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of that City, and this of a whole Nation, if God ſo bleſs it.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Work your Honours are herein moved to do; is but what the Lord commandeth to be done, though great and glorious, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving all Popiſh Rubbiſh out of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, that a throrow-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation may be made, that ſo the Anger of the Lord may be turned from this Nation: Therefore let not ten to two diſcourage you, (who have God's Promiſe on your ſide, that <hi>the Whore muſt be made deſolate)</hi> that the <hi>Canaanites</hi> or Popiſh Walls are ſtrong, and that your Oppoſers are power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as Giants: Neither let the oppoſition of the <hi>Tobiaſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> of the Times hinder the Work, ſeeing God opened the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi>'s heart to ſtrengthen the hand of the Lord's People in the figurative Work of the Lord's Building. And what hath the Lord done leſs on the heart of his Majeſty, (and we are bound to believe it is real) that hath encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged your Honours to take care of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion? and what care can be like that, to cleanſe it from all <hi>Popiſh Inventions</hi> either in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, or Service, or any other thing whatſoever in Worſhip, which is not found agreeable to the Rules of Chriſt's Teſtament: which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the Work of Reformation from Antichriſt's Apoſtacy, the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Reed of God's Word to meaſure the Spiritual Altars, Temple, and Worſhippers therein. For ſo long as the forbidden thing hid in the Camp of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> remained in <hi>Achan</hi>'s Tent, <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not ſtand before their Enemies: how then ſhall this Nation, ſo long as the forbidden thing of <hi>Popiſh Abominations</hi> is retained in the Camp or Tents of <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> ſtand before their Enemies, which the Doctrine of the Goſpel forbiddeth all Chriſtians not to taſte, touch, or handle in Worſhip? The neglect of this glorious Work commanded of God, in not making the <hi>Romiſh Whore utterly deſolate</hi> in the Nation, hath been the chief cauſe God is angry with us, in not only ſuffering ſo many Plots to be contrived to the utter ruine thereof, becauſe there is ſtill retained ſo many <hi>Popiſh Abominations</hi> in Miniſtry and Traditions as aforeſaid, the Fire of which hath kindled in the Boſom of <hi>Proteſtant Churches</hi> at this day all the Contentions in Religion, to the dividing <hi>Proteſtants</hi> one from the other into ſo many diverſities of opinions. Alſo it hath given ſtrong confidence to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to believe that ſuch <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as can without ſcruple of conſcience adhere to, and imbrace again ſo many <hi>Popiſh Abominations</hi> in Worſhip, which they once vomited up, ſhall in God's juſt Judgment be made, either by fraud or by force, to imbrace all the reſt of the Popiſh Abominations which our former Governours aboliſhed, to wit, the Lord Abbots, Cardinals, Jeſuits, Friers, and all other Reliques expelled with them, ſeeing the Meat is not worſe than the Broth; that ſo the head and tail of that beaſtly Clergy may be joyned together, when they are united to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34398:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> their younger Brethren the Arch and Lord Biſhops, as the Proverb is, <hi>Birds of a feather will not reſt in their motion till they come together:</hi> and then the deadly wound of the Beaſt will be again healed, to the Scorpion-like tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Plague <hi>(Rev.</hi> 9.) of all true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> if the King, with your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, be not the Phyſicians in God's hand to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> if ſomething of this nature be not done for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the ſhedding of innocent Blood, that if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> within us ſhould riſe, or their Accomplices invade us from without, the King's Majeſty with your Honours, would be pleaſed to make an Act, that all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> now (as was granted to the <hi>Jews</hi> in the days of K. <hi>Ahaſuerus)</hi> may without offence ſtand in their own defence in the preſervation of the lives of themſelves and their families, in what manner your Honours ſhall think fit. And this by God's Bleſſing will break the hearts of all Popiſh Plotters in their wicked deſigns; who for madneſs, inſtead of deſtroying <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> like the enemies of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> will deſtroy one another.</p>
            <p>O <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore that his Majeſty, with your Honours, would remember to follow the Example of that wiſe and good King <hi>Solomon,</hi> who firſt built the Lord's Houſe before he built his own. And K. <hi>David</hi> was grieved that himſelf ſhould dwell in an Houſe of Cedar, when the Ark of God remained under Curtains. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> could have no joy (tho the Kings Cupbearer) to ſee the City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> lie waſte. If then the King's Majeſty, with your Honours, would imitate theſe worthy Patrio's herein, <hi>in ſeeking firſt the Kingdom of God, and his Righteouſneſs,</hi> then all ſmaller things of Temporal Deliverances, and outward Benefits ſhall be added. Which God will ſtill make good to all true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> if they prefer the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem before their chiefeſt joy,</hi> Pſal. 137. as was made good to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who were a Nation in the midſt of Idolatrous Nations, as the true Churches of God are now, <hi>Holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in the midſt of the Nations: And ſo long as Chriſtians now, as God's People of old, do faithfully walk wi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h God in his true Faith and Worſhip, they are ſaid <hi>to dwell alone,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Faith and Worſhip among the Nations, Num. 34. 24. The want of theſe things now, amongſt <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> is proved by holy Scripture to be the ſame cauſe God is teſtifying to us, as to <hi>Judah</hi> of old, <hi>I have forſaken my Houſe, I have left my Heritage, I have given the dearly beloved of my ſoul into the hands of her enemies:</hi> Read Jer. 12 13. If there be not a ſpeedy turning to the ſtreight path of the Lord, in executing Judgment, and ſeeketh the Truth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 1. The deep ſenſe of which, may with the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> cauſe every true Chriſtian to ſay, <hi>O that my head were water, and eyes a fountain of tears, to weep day and night for the ſlain of the daughter of my people;</hi> and <hi>that he had in the Wilderneſs a lodging-place,</hi> that he might not behold the Sins<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bounding, or the Judgments coming on the Land: O then, before it be too late, that the King's Majeſty, with your Honours; and alſo the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would lay theſe things to heart. Seeing how unwilling the Lord is to deſtroy this Nation, not only by diſcovering the Plots, but alſo the Cauſe why God ſuffers them. Now, <hi>ſhall a Trumpet be blown in the City, and the people not be warned? Or is there any evil in a City</hi> (to wit, of puniſhment) <hi>and I have not done it, ſaith the Lord?</hi> Hoſ. 3. 6. <hi>Be wiſe therefore, O ye Kings, be inſtructed, ye Judges of the Earth; kiſs the</hi> Son, <hi>leſt he be angry, and ye eriſh from the way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> For he is the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, who can only crown you with Glory; which the Lord in his Mercy will beſtow, as he hath promiſed, on all that love him, and keep his Commandments.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humble Servant in all Chriſtian Duties, <hi>THO. WALL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
